A Guide to the Carneal and Johnston, Virginia Military Institute, Architectural Drawings and Plans, 1918-1984
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Carneal and Johnston, Virginia Military Institute, Architectural Drawings and Plans, 1918-1984
Library of Virginia
40198
721 sheets, Mostly linen and vellum, some blueprints, some Diazoprints, some tracing paper (114 x 89 cm. and smaller)
Carneal and Johnston (Richmond, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ballou, Justice, Upton, Architects, Glen Allen, Virginia, 7 August 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Leigh Carneal, Jr. and James Markam Ambler Johnston began their firm around 1908 after spending a year working independently out of the same office space. The firm went on to become one of the most prolific and long-established architectural practices in Virginia.
Carneal, born in Richmond on October 24, 1881, graduated in 1903 from the Virginia Military Institute. He began his architectural practice around 1906 following a three year stint as a clerk in his father's company, Sitterding-Carneal-Davis Company. Johnston, born in Rockbridge County on May 18, 1885, studied engineering at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and Cornell University before moving to Richmond in 1906. He worked at the Richmond Cedar Works for one year until he began his own architectural practice.
From 1908 until 1950, the firm of Carneal and Johnston (the firm was known as Carneal, Johnston, and Wright from 1928 through 1945, when Oscar Pendleton Wright was a partner) helped to mold the architectural environment of central Virginia, especially Richmond. Responsible for over 1300 buildings, Carneal and Johnston practiced in a wide-range of project types, from the mundane to the monumental. While they did execute some residential buildings, the firm generated a far greater number of public, commercial, and industrial structures. Some of their most notable structures include First Virginia Regiment Armory (1913), the Virginia Mutual Building (1919-1921), the Virginia State Office Building (1922-1923), Saint Joseph's Villa (thirteen buildings, 1930-1931), the Virginia War Memorial (1932), and various structures on the campuses of Richmond College (now the University of Richmond) and Virginia Military Institute.
The firm survived following the founders' retirements in the 1950s. Subsequent owners were Miles Cary Johnston, James Beck, and Raymond Browder who sold the firm to employees Carlos H. Costas, W. Fred Hughes III, and Kenneth E. Bunch in 1984. In 1999, the surviving firm of Carneal and Johnston merged with Ballou Justice and Upton, Architects, and ceased to exist as an architectural firm.
Scope and Content
The Carneal and Johnston Virginia Military Institute (VMI) architectural drawings and plans consist of 721 sheets. This represents approximately 56 separate commissions undertaken by the firm between 1918 and 1984 at the Lexington, Virginia, military school. Alexander Jackson Davis (1803-1892), a New York-born architect, originally planned VMI's barracks, professors' residences and other buildings during the mid-19th century. VMI was the first American college campus to be executed wholly in the Gothic Revival style. The bulk of the Carneal and Johnston material covers 1920 through 1976 and shows major renovations to existing buildings or new construction on the campus. The drawings depict elevations, floor plans, details, sections, and the like for VMI structures. Additionally, a few topographic and plat style maps are housed in the collection. The majority, if not all, of the correspondence from the Carneal and Johnston firm is no longer extant.
The drawings are identified by their title. The date given on the container list is taken from the earliest date on the drawing and does not represent any revisions or addenda which were added at a later time. Many of the drawing sets are noted as "As Built" plans, meaning that they show some aspect of the built work in its final form.
Arrangement
Finding aid is arranged by project title.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
Oversized, Alterations and Fireproofing Barracks (Commission # 860) and Alterations and Additions to Central Heating Plant (Commission # 675) placed on Roll 1 (4/J/2/7/1) Oversized, Drill Hall (Commission # 1023) and Topographic Map of Proposed Riding Hall [Drill Hall] (Commission # 1023) placed on Roll 2 (4/J/2/7/1)
Contents List
- Mess Hall, Alterations and Additions to, 5/1/1919, 6 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 1)
- Maury-Brook and Richardson Halls, Rehabilitation, 6/9/1964, 10 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 2)
- Maury-Brook Hall, Alterations to, 4/9/1934, 16 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 3)
- Power House, Alterations to, 6/24/1931, 29 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 4)
- Residence No. 1, 7/28/1927, 10 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 5)
- Power House, Alterations to, 08/1932, 7 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 6)
- Mess Hall Incinerator, 05/28/1934, 2 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 7)
- Jackson Hall, Swimming Pool, 10/25/1935, 14 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 7)
- Superintendent's Residence, Alterations and Additions to, 09/1924, 4 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 8)
- Officers' Quarters House-A, 06/1919, 3 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 8)
- Military Store and Tailor Shop, Alterations and Additions to, 04/04/1934, 17 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 9)
- Library Building, 06/20/1938, 33 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 10)
- Preston Library, Phase I Renovation of, 03/30/1973, 12 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 11)
- Boiler No. 3, 06/15/1938, 4 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 12)
- Cocke Hall, Alterations and Additions to, 07/31/1969, 13 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 12)
- Central Heating Plant, Alterations and Additions to, 07/1927, 7 sheets (Roll 1)
- Gymnasium for the VMI, 08/1925, 26 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 13)
- Mess Hall, 05/08/1934, 16 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 14)
- Utilities Building, 05/22/1934, 21 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 2, Folder 14)
- Stadium Toilets, 07/11/1947, 2 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 15)
- Stable, 04/11/1939, 7 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 15)
- Barracks, Additions to, 10/01/1942, 42 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 16)
- Barracks, Alterations and Fireproofing, 11/30/1935, 15 sheets (Roll 1)
- Preston Library, Additions and Alterations to, 04/20/1970, 37 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 17)
- Riding Hall [Drill Hall], Topographic Map of Proposed, 05/10/1941, 1 sheets (Roll 2)
- Drill Hall, 06/16/1941, 8 sheets (Roll 2)
- Preston Library, Assorted copies and tracings for, 1934-1984, 41 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 18)
- Engineering Hall, 06/02/1930, 34 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 19)
- Nichols Engineering Hall, New Annex to, 08/15/1966, 31 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 19)
- Jackson Memorial Hall, Renovations to, 07/01/1964, 24 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 19)
- Barracks, Electrical Renovations, 07/01/1966, 7 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 20)
- Nichols Engineering Hall, Phase I of Rehabilitation, 02/03/1976, 17 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 20)
- Nichols and Jackson Halls, Assorted drawings, tracings, and copies for, 1966-1974, 13 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 21)
- Old Military Science Building, Revisions to, 04/09/1968, 2 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 22)
- Science Building, 12/22/1950, 47 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 22)
- Science Hall, Alterations and Additions to, 08/15/1962, 34 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 23)
- Crozet Hall, Alterations to, 04/12/1973, 19 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 24)
- Retaining Wall and Niche, 01/15/1931, 2 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 24)
- Barracks, Alterations to, 07/22/1926, 2 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 23)
- Academic Building [Scott-Shipp Hall], 08/1918, 16 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 23)
- Barracks, Alterations and Additions to, 12/1922, 18 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 23)
- Residence for VMI, 11/28/1949, 17 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 25)
- Hospital, Alterations and Repairs to, 03/16/1950, 9 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 25)
- Bridge and Approach, 07/15/1929, 4 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 25)
- Chemistry Area between Richardson and Maury-Brooke Halls, Alterations in, 08/03/1962, 5 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 25)
- Barracks, Partial Concourse Air Conditioning, 05/01/1969, 2 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 25)
- Jackson Memorial Hall- Museum Floor, Renovations to, 05/10/1974, 1 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 21)
- Nichols Engineering Hall- Annex No. 1, Alterations to, 12/11/1968, 1 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 21)
- Nichols Engineering Hall, Computer Room, 09/05/1972, 1 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 3, Folder 21)
- Field House, Re-roofing of, 02/27/1973, 1 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 26)
- Scott-Shipp Hall, Auditorium Air Conditioning, 05/05/1973, 1 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 26)
- Observatory Foundation and Floor Slab, 05/27/1967, 1 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 26)
- Mallory Hall, Proposed Renovations to, 07/28/1972, 3 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 26)
- [Miscellaneous linen drawing], n.d., 1 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 26)
- Snead and Co. Library Bookstacks blueprints, 04/06/1938, 7 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 26)
- Barracks Room Occupants, 02/18/1925, 2 sheets (Map Case 1, Drawer 4, Folder 26)